<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached before the Generall Assembly at Glascoe in the kingdome of Scotland, the tenth day of Iune, 1610. By George Meriton Doctor of Diuinitie, and one of his Maiesties chaplaines</title>
            <author>Meriton, George, d. 1624.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1611</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 68 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 20 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A07454</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 17840</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S112673</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99847919</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99847919</idno>
            <idno type="VID">12987</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A07454)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 12987)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1354:17)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached before the Generall Assembly at Glascoe in the kingdome of Scotland, the tenth day of Iune, 1610. By George Meriton Doctor of Diuinitie, and one of his Maiesties chaplaines</title>
                  <author>Meriton, George, d. 1624.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[40] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by William Stansby for Henry Featherstone,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1611.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: A-E⁴.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:12987:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:12987:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SERMON PREACHED BE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>FORE THE GENERALL</p>
            <p>ASSEMBLY AT GLASCOE IN THE KINGDOME</p>
            <p>Of SCOTLAND, the tenth day of Iune, 1610.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> GEORGE MERITON <hi>Doctor of Diuinitie, and one of his Mateſties Chaplaines.</hi>
            </p>
            <figure>
               <q>THOV SHALT LABOR FOR PEACE PLEN<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>TIE</q>
            </figure>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON</hi> Printed by <hi>William Stansby</hi> for <hi>Henry Featherſtone.</hi> 1611.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:12987:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:12987:2"/>
            <head>A SERMON PREA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CHED BEFORE THE GE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NERALL ASSEMBLY AT Glaſcoe in the Kingdome of SCOT<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LAND, the tenth day of Iune, 1610.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>2. COR. 1. 12.</bibl>
                  <p>For our reioycing is this, the teſtimony of our conſcience.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His verſe is not complete in it ſelfe, but like the face of <hi>Ianꝰ,</hi> it looketh two wayes; <hi>backwards and forwards:</hi> hauing a reſpect vnto that which went before, and a reference alſo vnto the wordes which follow. It is not my purpoſe to handle it by way of relation, but to take it at large in the
<pb facs="tcp:12987:3"/>
nature of a propoſition. <hi>Our reioycing is this, the testimony of our conſcience.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There are three kinde of people in the world, which are <hi>Reioycers:</hi> the firſt they reioyce; but it is not in a <hi>conſcience:</hi> the ſecond reioyce in a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience (as they call it,) but yet without a <hi>testimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie:</hi> the third are like to <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Timathy</hi> in this place: their reioycing is this, the teſtimony of their <hi>Conſcience.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Of the former ſort, there are multitudes euery where, in euery Kingdome: The world is full of<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pro.</hi> 15. 21.</note> 
               <hi>Solomons</hi> fooliſh reioycers. The ambitious min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded man, who may fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ly be reſembled vnto the <hi>empty ballance,</hi> that will alwaies be aloſt; he reioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth in honour, and it is happines to get aduance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pro.</hi> 28.</note>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 12.</note> The wiſe foole, (that is) the rich man, and greedy miſer, whoſe eyes are blinded with the duſt of the earth, and who gathereth matter together with the <hi>Phoenix,</hi> to conſume himſelfe; hee ſayth vnto his ſoule, Liue at eaſe, eate, drinke, glut thy ſelfe with pleaſures; his ioye is in thoſe things which S. <hi>Paul</hi> accounteth but dongue. It were too long a voyage for me, to runne ouer the whole world, and to proſecute particulars. In one word, all vngodly men, reioyce in doing euill, and take great delight in wicked things. <hi>Pro</hi> 2. 14. But the ioy of theſe, is but like the foppe of <hi>Iudas,</hi> which made a wider way for the Diuell to enter into him, <hi>Delectatio non gaudium,</hi> ſaith <hi>Aquinas,</hi> a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light, not a ioy; or if it be a ioy, it is but <hi>gaudium vanitatis, non veritatis,</hi> ſaith <hi>S. Augustine,</hi> a vain and
<pb facs="tcp:12987:3"/>
an empty ioy, without all ſound and inward com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort: much like the merry madneſſe of drunken men, who are very pleaſant for a time, but recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penced with loathſomneſſe a long while after: ſuch are all the drunken delights of the world. <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>omi,</hi> ſweet at the firſt, pleaſant in the beginning,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ruth.</hi> 1. 20.</note> but <hi>Mara</hi> and <hi>amara,</hi> bitter at the laſt, loathſome in the ending<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as <hi>Philo Iudeus</hi> calleth them, bitter ſweet things; not much vnlike the ioy of <hi>Dauid,</hi> after his return from the ſlaughter of the <hi>Amalekites</hi> in <hi>Ziglag,</hi> whoſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> wine was mingled<note place="margin">2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> with water, whoſe mirth was turned into mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning with the ſudden newes of the death of <hi>Saul</hi> and <hi>Ionathan.</hi> All reioycing which proceedeth not from a good conſcience, is (ſaith S. <hi>Paul</hi>) but<note place="margin">2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. 12.</note> the ioy of the face, and not of the heart; and it e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uermore concludeth with that ſame ſentence of a foole, <hi>Non pataram,</hi> I had not thought. For as true ioy hath his foundation in the <hi>Center,</hi> and is ſpread from the <hi>Center</hi> of the heart, throughout all the parts of the ſoule, by the ſpirit; ſo falſe ioy comme<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h from the <hi>Circumference,</hi> it is enforced vpon the affections by externall obiects, it reſteth not in the <hi>Center,</hi> it is not ſeated in the heart: And therefore though for a time it may cheere the face, yet if the conſcience be bad, it can neuer fill the breaſt. The ioy of a wicked man, ſaith <hi>Iob,</hi> it is<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iob</hi> 20. 5.</note> 
               <hi>inſtar puncti,</hi> like a little point or pricke. Firſt, in reſpect of a <hi>Circle;</hi> a little point is many times compaſſed with a very great <hi>Circle:</hi> ſuch is the ioy of the wicked, like a point in a <hi>Circle,</hi> compaſſed
<pb facs="tcp:12987:4"/>
round about with a thouſand euils. He may haue the mappe of heauen in his face, but he carrieth the mappe of holl in his heart. He may haue <hi>Iera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem</hi> the Citie of peace in his forehead, but he beareth <hi>Babylon,</hi> that is, confuſion in his ſoule. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, it is <hi>inſtar puncti,</hi> in regard of that point or minute of time which it laſteth, <hi>Qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d incipiendo deſinit eſſe, &amp; deſinendo incipit,</hi> ſaith <hi>Gregory:</hi> which is very ſhort, and ſuddenly endeth; according to<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Job</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>1. 13.</note> that of <hi>Iob,</hi> They ſpend their dayes in wealth, and in the turning of a hand they goe downe to hell. Thirdly, it is <hi>inſtar puncti,</hi> in regard of the making of it: for as a point or pricke is made with prick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; ſo is the ioy of the wicked ioyned with mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning. <hi>Riſus eum dolore miſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>tur:</hi> in laughing the<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pro.</hi> 14. 13.</note> heart is ſorrowfull, and the end of their mirth is much heaulneſſe. To conclude this point; where there is <hi>Ignis</hi> and <hi>Vermis,</hi> that is, where there is a helliſh and guilty conſcience, there ſuppoſe to be (if you pleaſe) the greateſt ioy that can be, eyther in honors, or wealth, or pleaſures, or knowledge, or in any thing elſe of higheſt title and preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue in the world, yet is all but like the ſacrifice of <hi>Prometheus,</hi> which was nothing but drie bones beſmeared with fat, or like to gilded bookes full of bloudy <hi>Tragedies.</hi> In the middeſt of all iollities, the conſsience many times crieth out, not onely<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 8. 19.</note> as the <hi>Magicians</hi> did, <hi>Digitus Dei est hic,</hi> the finger of God is here, but alſo as it was ſaid of <hi>Totilas</hi> the <hi>Gothe, Flagellum Dei est hic,</hi> the ſcourge of God is here: and the Diuell affrighteth the ſoule as <hi>Hani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ball</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:12987:4"/>
did the <hi>Romans. Haniball ad port as,</hi> the Diuell is at our doores. Let no man therefore euer com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort himſelfe in any worldly reioycing, vnleſſe it be ioyned with the teſtimony of a good con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience.</p>
            <p>The ſecond kinde of reioycers reioyce in a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, (as they call it) but yet without a teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie: And as the former ſort are vngodly and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane, ſo theſe are ſeeming-religious; a conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence they ſay, doth guide and admoniſh them. Of whom I may well ſay, as the olde man in the <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy</hi> ſpeaketh of certaine things, which his yong ſonne a yonker did ouermuch affect: <hi>Nec optima haec ſunt, ne<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> vt ego aequum cenſeo, verum meltora ſunt quem quae deterrima,</hi> Theſe are not of the beſt faſhion, nor as my ſelfe could wiſh, yet better then thoſe which are the worſt of all. So theſe are not of S. <hi>Pauls</hi> company, the beſt kinde of reioycers, nor yet neere that ſound and ſweete comfort, which wee ought to ſeeke after; <hi>ſed meliores ſunt quam qui deterrimi,</hi> they are better then the ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, which make a Ship-wracke of conſcience, and are the worſt of all: thoſe haue their conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences ſeared vp <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>a iudgement moſt fearefull and lamentable. Theſe haue them polluted and trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.</note> ſometimes perhappes like the raging Sea,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Tit.</hi> 1. 15.</note> which cannot reſt, whoſe waters caſt vp myre and<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſay.</hi> 57. 20.</note> dirt, blinded in their vnderſtandings, and errone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous in their wils: and therefore as S. <hi>Iames</hi> ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth, vnſtable in all their wayes. I doe not denie<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jam.</hi> 1. 8.</note> but that theſe men haue their kindes of ioy, yet let
<pb facs="tcp:12987:5"/>
vs looke a while into the cauſes of errour in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, the better to iudge of the manner of their reioycing. The firſt cauſe of error, is <hi>Ignorance;</hi> and of this ranke are ſilly and ſimple men, who out of ignorance and weakeneſſe, being deluded eyther by themſelues, or by others, do apprehend things for bad, which are good; and for good, thoſe which are bad, which deceiueth their ſoules and cauſeth their willes for to ſinne. <hi>Lippientibus</hi> ſaith <hi>Tertullian, ſingularis Lucerna numeroſa vide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur.</hi> Bleare eyed men ſpie two Candles where there is but one. <hi>Ignorant</hi> conſciences are bleare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eyed; yea, ſometimes ſtone blinde, they cannot poſſibly diſcerne aright: and the ioy of theſe, it is but like a mans that walketh in a darke and clou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioh.</hi> 12.</note> night, who knoweth not whither he wande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth, full of errour, of doubting, of darkeneſſe: for if the vnderſtanding (the light of a man be dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned how great is that darknes? It is our Sauiour that putteth the queſtion, as being a darknes fitter to be admired, then eaſie to be eſteemed. The ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond cauſe of errour in <hi>Conſcience</hi> is <hi>Pride,</hi> which<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 6. 13.</note> worketh ſpecially in thoſe, who, as the <hi>wiſe man</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pro.</hi> 1. 31.</note> ſpeaketh, do eate of the fruit of their owne hands, and are filled with their owne deuices. <hi>Quibus res ſordid<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> est,</hi> ſaith <hi>Sen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ca, trita &amp; vulgari via viuere,</hi> vnto whom the olde way of the Chriſtian world, ſo generally followed of all, is either accounted none or nothing worth. It is reported by the <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>et of Chiron,</hi> a new fangled fellow, that he was wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie of immorrality, and wiſhed to die. The <hi>Athe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:12987:5"/>
hauing their fill of new wines, for nouelties ſake, ſaith <hi>Plutarch,</hi> would needes drinke oyles. <hi>Zeuxes,</hi> as <hi>Plinie</hi> relateth, would not willingly paint any common picture but <hi>Centaures</hi> and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed Monſters<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſuch giddy men are there in Gods Church, iuſt of the ſtampe of theſe, <hi>qui ex re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus nouis claritatem famae venantur,</hi> ſaith <hi>Gregory,</hi> who take delight by their miſ-ſhapen opinions, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the vulgar ſort to magnifie themſelues. Theſe are greatly puffed vp with a ſwelling ioy, but yet without true ſubſtance, like to their proud vnderſtandings, their peruerſe wils, and their miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>informed conſciences. The third cauſe of error is inordinate affection, euidently ſeene in thoſe who yeelde to their owne deſires, and are there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore men of a large and a ſtretching conſcience, hauing their iudgements periſhed with a longing appetite, becauſe as <hi>Seneca</hi> ſaith truely, <hi>perit omne Iudicium cum res tranſit in affectum;</hi> when any thing is ſeated in the Pange and heat of affection, the iudgement concerning that matter, whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer it be is vtterly decayed. Theſe thinke it a part of good ſeruice done to God, a meere caſe of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience to follow ſo farre the ſway of their vnbrid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led affections, as eyther with <hi>Saul</hi> in the olde Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament, to kill the <hi>Prophets,</hi> becauſe hee hated them; or with <hi>Paul</hi> in the new Teſtament, to make hauocke of the Church of Chriſt for loue vnto the Iewes. Thus many (according to their ſeuerall deſires) tranſported with paſſion, and hauing their conſciences and affections of equal breadth, grow
<pb facs="tcp:12987:6"/>
preſumptuous in their actions; and being decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued by the ſlattery of their owne hearts, haue a large but a very looſe reioycing. The laſt cauſe of errour is fearefulneſſe of minde, which contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cteth the ſoule to an ouer-narrow, and too ſtrict a ſcantling; entertayning cauſe of feare where no feare is. Incident vnto this errour are men of perplexed mindes, trembling at a ſhaddow, and wounding their ſoules with ſtrawes. Vnto whom<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 8. 26.</note> I may fitly ſpeake, as <hi>Chriſt</hi> did once to his, Why are ye ſo fearefull, O ye of little faith? The aunci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent &amp; reuerend name of a Biſhop is as a skarebug vnto them, they ſtart at it as at an <hi>Affrican Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter,</hi> newly preſented vnto the view of the world. Theſe abridge themſelue in many things of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian liberty, their feare cauſeth miſconſtruction, and their conſciences being ful of cowardiſe, their ioy is like vnto them, alwayes pinching, and ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with perplexity. To conclude this point al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, that heauenly conſolation which S. <hi>Paul</hi> felt, and which euery one of vs is bound to ſeeke after, it is not to be found in an ignorant, a peruerſe, a preſumptuous, a perplexed conſcience: we may ſay of all theſe, as the <hi>Angels</hi> ſaid to the women<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 24.</note> concerning Chriſt, Why ſeeke you the liuing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the dead? a liuing ioy in a dying <hi>Conſcience? Non eſt hic,</hi> it is not here. But our reioycing, ſaith the Apoſtle, is this, the reſtimony of our conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence. Sith then this vnſpeakeable ioy of heart can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be had, but where there is a teſtimony, let vs now enquire what this teſtimony of conſcience
<pb facs="tcp:12987:6"/>
ſhould be, which is thus requiſite to a ſound and a hearty ioy.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Conſcience</hi> by <hi>Diuines</hi> is defined to be a know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge ioyned with a knowledge; whereby we know what we know, and vnderſtand that of our ſelues which God knoweth of vs. By naturall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition it is placed betwixt man and God: vnder God, and therefore doth it yeelde all ſubiection vnto him: aboue man, and therefore hath it a po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer ouer him, to accuſe or excuſe him, to fill him full of ſorrow, or exceeding ioy. In the exerciſing of which power, it vſeth a teſtimony. Now euen in the Ciuill Law we are forbidden to admit of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery kind of Teſtimony <hi>promiſcually. Vox vnius, est vox nullius,</hi> ſaith <hi>Baldus,</hi> one witneſſe is no wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. <hi>Vniteſti ne Catoni quidem credendum eſt,</hi> ſaith <hi>Hierome,</hi> If <hi>Cato</hi> himſelfe ſhould ſpeake alone, who for his integrity was feigned by the Poet <hi>Iuuenall</hi> to come down from heauen (<hi>Tertius de Celo cecidit Cato</hi>) he were not alone to bee beleeued. In the mouth of two or three witneſſes ſhall euery word ſtand, <hi>Deu.</hi> 19. <hi>v.</hi> 15. Firſt then, in the cauſe of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience eſpecially, there is required a competent number, which muſt make a teſtimony. Though one apple be enough to manifeſt the life of a tree, yet doth not one Swallow make a Summer, ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is one good motion of the minde (though it be of grace) able to giue vnto vs a ſound cauſe of ioy. And as plurality of witneſſes muſt concurre to make a teſtimony, ſo againe is it needefull that they be duly qualified. The <hi>Ciuilian</hi> telleth vs, that
<pb facs="tcp:12987:7"/>
vnto ſufficient witneſſes, theſe things are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired:</p>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Aetas, conditio, ſexus, diſcretio, fama,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>At<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> fortuna, fides, in teſtibus iſta requiras.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <p>Age, condition, ſexe, diſcretion, fame, eſtate, and faith are to be obſcrued in euery witnes. And as good choyce ought to be made in any caſe in the world, then in this of conſcience principally, no one thing being of greater conſequence in the life of man, and wherunto (as <hi>Baldus</hi> ſpeaketh of Wils and Teſtaments) there may ſoone be admitted, <hi>vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tium inu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſibile,</hi> a ſecret and a hidden errour. Here then at once are excluded, as inſufficient in the Court of <hi>Conſcience</hi> for the diſpatch of this office, all opinions and variable conceits of men, al con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſions which are onely probable and coniectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall; for theſe are childiſh and in their nonage. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, the rebellious and vnbridled affections of the heart, which by their condition are no free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, but in bondage vnto reaſon, are like <hi>Knights of the poſt,</hi> which abuſe the Court; and therefore good reaſon is there, that when they be too for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward they ſhould bee reiected. If <hi>Concupiſcence</hi> would become <hi>Amica Curtae,</hi> a bufie informer in the Court of <hi>Conſcience,</hi> truſt her not, ſhe is as <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formers</hi> are, corrupt and infamous. If <hi>Choler</hi> be ſtirring, follow it not, it is but a madde and bed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lam paſſion, like furious zeale without diſcretion, and giue no fit teſtimony for a reioycing conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence. <hi>Loue, hatred, enuy, malice,</hi> and the reſt, are wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manniſh and vnfaithfull: and he that truſteth his
<pb facs="tcp:12987:7"/>
owne heart is not wiſe. <hi>Prou.</hi> 28. <hi>ver.</hi> 26. <hi>Abraham</hi> begat <hi>Iſaac</hi> when as <hi>Sara</hi> was olde; the ſpirit be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getteth ioy, when the affections are the weakeſt. The teſtimony of our <hi>Conſcience</hi> muſt be of good fame, good yeares, free, faithfull, diſcreet, euermore ioyned with verity, iudgement, and iuſtice, as <hi>Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rome</hi> obſerueth vpon the fourth Chapter of <hi>Iere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie.</hi> If all theſe then be inſufficient and deceit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, whither ſhall we turne vs to get this able te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Damaſcene</hi> in his <hi>Logique,</hi> aſcribeth this duety to knowledge in the vnderſtanding; which then it rightly performeth, when as euery thought is brought into obedience, and all imaginations are ſubdued vnto it. 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 10. <hi>ver.</hi> 5. It is an vncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouleable <hi>Axiome,</hi> both in <hi>Philoſophy</hi> and <hi>Diuini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie,</hi> that there is <hi>nulla or dinata actio quae proficiſcitur à voluntate in intellectum,</hi> that there is no action wel ordered which commeth from the will, to the vnderſtanding, but the vnderſtanding muſt firſt beget it, and then the will bring it forth: he that will ſing in the ſpirit, muſt firſt haue his vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding tuned. Sing prayſes vnto God, ſaith <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid,</hi> euery one that hath vnderſtanding. It is a<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 47. 7.</note> ſpeech that ſauoureth of little learning, to ſay that a man hath more conſcience then ſcience; the contrary is too often true, more ſcience then con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience: for <hi>Conſcientia is concludens ſcientta,</hi> a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluding knowledge; which doth neceſſarily im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port a precedent vnderſtanding. There muſt be il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumination in the braine, light in the head, before
<pb facs="tcp:12987:8"/>
there can be <hi>ſanctification</hi> in the will, true heate in the heart; and if there be no proportion betwixt heat and light, the ouerplus of heate which is in many is but <hi>ignis fat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>s,</hi> a fooliſh fire <hi>Iohn Baptist</hi> is called a burning and a <hi>ſhining</hi> light, firſt bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Job.</hi> 5. 35.</note> then ſhining: It is true, if he be conſidered with reſpect vnto others; but take him in himſelfe alone, then was he <hi>Lucens, &amp; ardens,</hi> firſt enlight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, then enflamed. <hi>Lucere vanum, ardere parum, lucere &amp; ardere perfectum,</hi> ſaith S. <hi>Bernard.</hi> God alwayes beginneth to renue a man in his vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding: that which by our fall was firſt corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, is firſt repaired. The vnderſtanding was firſt blinded by the Serpents ſubtlety, and there doth God beginne to worke euery good action. And therefore it is not will, affection, coniecture, opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, or any inferior power of the ſoule, but know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge in the mind that muſt yeeld a teſtimony to a reioycing conſcience. And yet not all kinde of knowledge: not naturall; for then might the Pagan or Heathen man reioyce: not <hi>Legall;</hi> for then were there ioy in the bare killing letter of the Law: but <hi>Euangelicall,</hi> begotten in vs by the ſpirite of GOD, and ſowne in our hearts by the preaching of his Worde. True it is that by our creation wee had a three-folde knowledge, which was moſt excellent: firſt, of all things cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated: ſecondly, of our Creatour: thirdly, of our ſelues. But by our tranſgreſsion we are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come like brute beaſts, voyde of vnderſtanding. We haue a threefold ignorance, in ſtead of our
<pb facs="tcp:12987:8"/>
knowledge. Firſt, of all things created: Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, of God: Thirdly, of our ſelues. Hence is it that ſinnes are ſaid by <hi>S. Auguſtine</hi> to be the ſoules darkneſſe, that <hi>Gregory</hi> calleth offendors fooles, and <hi>S. Paul</hi> the wiſedome of the world, enmity vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God. The Mappe of the whole world, is witti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly compriſed in the compaſſe of a fooles hood, and <hi>Noſce teipſum</hi> in the front thereof; which may ſerue to tell vs, what naturally we are. Thoſe <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimalia ſapientie,</hi> as <hi>Tertullian</hi> ſtileth the <hi>Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers,</hi> thoſe profound wizards of the world, though they had a ſlender gheſſe, that <hi>Minerua</hi> ſhould come from the head of <hi>Iupiter, true wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome</hi> from God; yet they feigned her to be a Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin, vnknowen of <hi>man. Socrates</hi> who was eſteemed the wiſeſt amongſt them, confeſſed of himſelfe, that he knew nothing at all. Many were of opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, that all things are but opinions. Thus euen in naturall things, are we ignorant in our know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, not much vnlike a ſmoaking fornace, which voideth vp plenty of fume, yet is voide of light; yea our fooliſh hearts are full of darkneſſe. <hi>Rom.</hi> 1. <hi>verſ.</hi> 21. As therefore in certaine Cities among the Iewes (as <hi>Philo</hi> reporteth) it was not permit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to a man of a ſcandalous life, to put vp his pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition to the <hi>Senate</hi> by himſelfe, but was to moue by another, whoſe life, and fame, was neuer im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peached; ſo ſtandeth the caſe with our vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding. Naturally it is out of temper, and defiled: and therefore in the deliuery of this teſtimony it may not ſpeake, but by <hi>proxie</hi> (who is vpright and
<pb facs="tcp:12987:9"/>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iohn</hi> 2 <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 5.</note>incorrupt) euen the <hi>Spirit</hi> of God, ſpeaking by the word of God. The conſcience muſt beare me wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe by the ſpirit ſaith <hi>S. Paul. Rom.</hi> 9. <hi>verſ.</hi> 1. and then let iudgement, and will, and affections con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curre, we are ſure to haue a true teſtimony, and a reioycing conſcience: when as the <hi>Spirit</hi> of God doth teſtifie vnto our ſpirits, that we are Saints and Sonnes of God. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. <hi>verſ.</hi> 16. And now are we come to that, which was <hi>S. Paules</hi> reioycing, not in any worldly or outward things: nor yet in an erroneous, or miſinformed conſcience; but in the excuſing ſenſe of his ſoule, in regard of God, and in the integrity of his heart, in reſpect of man.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Prouerb.</hi> 10.</note> 
               <hi>Wiſedome</hi> did guide him, and therefore he walked<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iohn</hi> 1.</note> boldly; the ſpirit did beare him witneſſe, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he reioyced truly; he built vp a Conſiſtory in his ſoule with iudgement, cleanſed it with repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, and adorned it with loue, and ſo reioyced in the teſtimony of his conſcience. This kinde of <hi>Conſcience</hi> 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 2. is called a good conſcience, and in the ſecond to <hi>Tim.</hi> 1. a pure conſcience: not becauſe it is free from the ſtaine of <hi>Originall ſinne,</hi> for it is a certaine truth which <hi>S. Auguſtine</hi> ſetteth downe in the thirteenth Chapter of his <hi>Enchiridi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: Malum eſt quod bonum, &amp; bonum quod malum.</hi> That in this world we haue good mingled with our euill, and euill with our good. We ſee in part, we know in part, and our <hi>Conſcience</hi> is imperfect, yet good, and pure, being neither iuſtly accuſed for things which are paſt, nor vniuſtly delighted with things which are preſent. <hi>Bona, ordinatione</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:12987:9"/>
               <hi>affectionis, pura excluſione criminis: bona, ſine dupli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citate intentionis, pura, ſine remorſione vermu</hi> (as a Schooleman ſpeaketh) This kinde of <hi>Conſcience</hi> among the ancient Fathers, hath honorable titles giuen vnto it, they call it a field of <hi>bleſſedneſſe,</hi> a garden of <hi>delight,</hi> the ioy of <hi>Angels,</hi> the houſe of the <hi>holy Ghoſt,</hi> and the Paradiſe of the <hi>Soule.</hi> The ioy that floweth from it, is (ſaith <hi>S. Bernard</hi>) a <hi>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia,</hi> that is, a <hi>latitia,</hi> a ſurpaſſing ioy, which maketh a mans heart farre wider then his mouth. <hi>Chilon, Sophocles,</hi> and <hi>Dionyſius,</hi> died vpon a ſodaine (ſaith <hi>Pli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ie</hi>) with a greatneſſe of ioy, yet was their ioy but a wretched ſorrow, in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pariſon of the good, and pure ioy of an <hi>honeſt conſcience.</hi> This is no light, nor loude laughter, <hi>res ſeuera eſt, verum gau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dium, &amp; maximum aliquando, cum parum videtur blandum.</hi> True ioy is ſober, and ſeaſoned with gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uity, and then many times at the higheſt, when he that feeleth it, ſeemeth to be at the loweſt. Wine may make a man haue a merry heart, yet in the middeſt of mirth, there may be ſadneſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e in the <hi>conſcience.</hi> Sinne may make a man haue a heauy heart, yet in the middeſt of heauineſſe, there may be ioy in the <hi>conſcience. Paenitens ſemper dolet:</hi> there is the houſe of <hi>Mourning; &amp; de dolore ſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per gaudet</hi> (ſaith <hi>S. Auguſtine</hi>) here is the houſe of <hi>reioycing.</hi> So as a good conſcience, euen in mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning reioyceth: all the ſorrowes in the world can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not make it wholly ſadde: yea ſuch is the force of it, as it turneth ſorrow and bitterneſſe into ioy: Yee ſhall ſorrow (ſaith our <hi>Sauiour</hi> to his diſciples)<note place="margin">
                  <hi>John</hi> 16. 20.</note>
               <pb facs="tcp:12987:10"/>
but your ſorrow ſhall be turned into ioy. <hi>Homers Nepenthes</hi> was ſaid to haue a ſpeciall force in it, to take griefe away, but it had not the power to turne griefe into ioy. Whereas ſo many <hi>Croſſes,</hi> were<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 5. 41.</note> ſo many <hi>conſolations</hi> vnto <hi>Chriſts Apoſtles.</hi> They triumphed in their afflictions, for that they were thought worthy to ſuffer them for their Maſters ſake. This made <hi>poore Iob</hi> (as <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſpeaketh of him) more happy <hi>in ſtercore,</hi> on the top of a dunghill: then <hi>Adam</hi> was <hi>in nemore,</hi> in the mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt of <hi>Paradiſe:</hi> becauſe (as himſelfe ſaith) his<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Job</hi> 27. 6.</note> heart did not reproue him all his dayes. And wheras the pleaſure of the world turned <hi>Lots</hi> wife into a pillar of <hi>Salt,</hi> the delight of <hi>conſcience</hi> tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth the pillar of Salt into <hi>Lots</hi> wife: ſo that <hi>Lot</hi> for a ſalt pillar ſhall haue a ſweet wife: for his grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt griefe, an exceeding comfort. <hi>Salomon</hi> could not well tell, what better to compare this <hi>conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Prouerb.</hi> 15.</note> vnto, then to a feaſt. A good <hi>Conſcience</hi> (ſaith he) is a continuall feaſt: what is more pleaſant, and more abounding in mirth then a ſolemne feaſt? how can we celebrate the remembrance of any thing better, then by a feaſt? <hi>Pharao</hi> and <hi>Herod</hi> vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon their birth dayes, could make but a feaſt. <hi>Ahaſuerus</hi> ſhewed all his royaltie by feaſting his Princes and Nobles of his Prouinces. So did <hi>Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſar</hi> after his triumphs: who is ſaid by <hi>Plutarch,</hi> to haue feaſted the <hi>Romans,</hi> at two and twenty thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand tables. And how doth the Church of <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſolemnize her <hi>Memorials,</hi> of the infinite mercies of God beſtowed vpon her, (as of the <hi>Birth, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:12987:10"/>
               <hi>Aſcenſion, &amp;c.</hi> of <hi>Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> but by her ſolemne feaſts? A good <hi>Conſcience</hi> is a good <hi>feaſt.</hi> The gueſts are the Trinity, <hi>Father, Sonne,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Apoc.</hi> 3.</note> and <hi>holy Ghoſt:</hi> The Miniſters are the <hi>Angels:</hi> the<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hebr.</hi> 1.</note> cheare, meate, and wine, (the word and <hi>Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi>)<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.</note> 
               <hi>Prouerb.</hi> 9. The <hi>Muſique gaudium Spiritus ſancti,</hi> the ioy and peace of the <hi>holy Ghoſt. O feſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>us dies hominis,</hi> bleſſed feſtiuall day. But what talke I of a day? it is continuall. <hi>Adonaiah</hi> made a feaſt,<note place="margin">1. <hi>King's</hi> 1.</note> but when <hi>Salomon</hi> was proclaimed <hi>King,</hi> he was daunted vpon that ſodaine newes. <hi>Belſhazar</hi> fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Dan.</hi> 5.</note> and carouſed Iuſtily; but when he ſaw the <hi>Palme</hi> of the hand, that wrot vpon the wall, <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ne, Mene, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ek<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l, Vph<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>rſin,</hi> his ioynts were loofened, and his knees ſmot together. The feaſt of <hi>Ahaſue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heſter</hi> 1. 4.</note> laſted but a hundred and foureſcore dayes. <hi>Sed vis ſemper epulari, vis <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>unquam triſtis eſſe?</hi> or (as <hi>Seneca</hi> ſaith) wil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> thou turne the whole yeare into <hi>December?</hi> keepe a continuall feaſt, and euer bee merry? Walke then worthy of thy vocation, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto thou art called, keepe a good conſcience to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards God, and vnblameable before men. For a good <hi>conſcience</hi> is a continuall feaſt. The meate<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iohn</hi> 6. 33.</note> periſheth not, and the bread is the bread of life. <hi>Et tanto amplius eſuritur quanto amplius comeditur:</hi> the more we ea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e, the more we may. The ioy is<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iohn</hi> 16. 22.</note> euerlaſting, and neuer ſhal any depriue vs thereof<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Et huic comparata, omnis iucunditas maeror eſt, omnis ſuanitas, dolor omne dulce amarum,</hi> saith <hi>S. Bernard:</hi> It is a ioy alone, beyond all compariſon. The <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet Eſay</hi> reſembleth it to the ioy of harueſt, and to<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſay</hi> 9. 3.</note>
               <pb facs="tcp:12987:11"/>
the reioycing of men, that diuide the ſpoile. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deede a husbandman hauing (after much toile and trauaile) long liued in expectation, ſeeing a good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly crop, white vnto the harueſt, cuts downe his corne, bindeth it vp in ſheaues, and bringeth it home with ſignes, and ſongs, and ſhoutes of ioy. When the <hi>Aegyptians</hi> were ouer throwen in the red ſea, then ſang <hi>Moſes</hi> and the children of <hi>Iſrael:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 15.</note> 
               <hi>Miriam</hi> alſo tooke a Timbrell in her hand, and all the women came out after her with Timbrels and daunces: there was a generall ioy, for a generall deliuerance: and yet for all that no ſpoile diuided: but when a bloudy battaile is ſought, the victory obtained, the citty entred, the houſes rifled, the riches poſſeſſed, the enimy vanquiſhed, O then my ſoule thou haſt marched valiantly, the heart is filled with gladneſſe, and the mouth with laugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and the earth doth ring with the ſound of war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like melodie. Theſe bee ſome ſhadowes of the ioyes of a good conſcience: but the ſubſtance is<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 33.</note> nothing neare expreſſed. <hi>Dauid</hi> ſetteth downe three degrees of this <hi>Spirituall ioy.</hi> The firſt is <hi>(gaudete)</hi> reioyce: the ſecond <hi>(exultate)</hi> skip and leape for ioy: the third is <hi>(iubilate)</hi> a word that commeth of <hi>Iobel,</hi> which ſignifieth the confuſed noiſe of <hi>Cornets,</hi> or <hi>Rammes hornes,</hi> made in the yeare of <hi>Iubilee.</hi> And this is ſuch a kinde of ioy (ſaith <hi>Gregory</hi>) <hi>quod nec ſupprimatur nec exprimatur:</hi> which can be neither ſuppreſſed nor expreſſed: or if it may be expreſſed, <hi>voce tantum exprimatur, ſed verbis non explicetur:</hi> It is a rauiſhing ioy, which
<pb facs="tcp:12987:11"/>
may breake forth out of the mouth in a confuſed noiſe; yet is not the mouth able to expreſſe that, which the heart conceiueth. What ſhould I ſay more? Put all the ioyes of the world together, and they are not able to counteruaile a reioycing <hi>Conſcience:</hi> O bleſſed <hi>Paul</hi> then, and moſt happy men and women are thoſe, whoſe reioycing is this, the teſtimony of their conſcience.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Doctrines</hi> which I raiſe from hence are partly (generall) for our inſtruction, partly (ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all) for the preſent occaſion.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Generall Doctrine.</head>
               <p>FIrſt, hereby we learne what a good <hi>Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence</hi> is; not a ſorrowing conſcience, or one that tortureth the ſoule, and teareth the hart in pieces, proceeding from the ſenſe of ſinne, and apprehenſion of the heauy wrath of God againſt vs for the ſame; but <hi>Conſcientia ſine offendiculo,</hi> a<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Act.</hi> 24. 16.</note> cleere conſcience is a good conſcience, which is not hindered from reioycing. The conſcience which accuſeth may bee many times, and is in Gods children, a ſtep vnto that which abſolueth and feeleth ioy; but where there is a ſorrow for ſinne without hope of grace, where there is a kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling by the olde man, and not a quickening by the new; if we feele the ſentence of death in our ſoules and not of life in our Sauior: although we ſhould recount vnto God all our ſinnes ouer, and ouer againe in the anguiſh and bitternes of our ſoules;
<pb facs="tcp:12987:12"/>
though wee ſhould lament like Dragons, and mourne like Oſtriches (as the <hi>Prophet Micah</hi> ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth)<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Micah.</hi> 1. 8.</note> yet haue we but that part of <hi>conſcience</hi> which euen the wicked and reprobates haue. <hi>Cainc, Saul, Iud<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> were greatly grieued for their ſinnes. <hi>Eſau</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Hebr.</hi> 12. 17.</note> lift vp his voyce and wept bitterly, yet could he find no place of repentance, and ſo by conſequent for peace of <hi>Conſcience,</hi> though he ſought it with<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Apoc.</hi> 7. 13.</note> teares. The good conſcience then excuſeth, abſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth, reioyceth, and the <hi>Saints</hi> in heauen follow the <hi>Lambe,</hi> not in blacke but in white roabes: the beſt men are no mourners, but reioycers; <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyce</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Theſ.</hi> 1. 5.</note> alwayes (ſaith S. <hi>Paul</hi> to the <hi>Theſſalonians,</hi> and to the <hi>Philippians</hi>) Reioyce in the Lord al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Phil.</hi> 4.</note> and againe I ſay reioyce.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, hence wee are taught that it is not lawfull to keepe our conſciences to our ſelues, but we muſt reioyce or glory in them; for ſo the word ſignifieth. S. <hi>Pauls</hi> conſcience did appeare by his glorying in it, <hi>tanta deb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t eſſe eius plenitudo, vt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net ab animo in habitum, vt eructet è conſcientia, in ſuperficiem,</hi> as <hi>Tertullian</hi> writeth of the modeſty of women; it ought to appeare in outward behaui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our. Away then with all cloſe and lurking conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences, of which there is no certainty to what way they encline<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                  <hi>Conſcientia proà re vult &amp; conſpici.</hi> It is not affraid of the light, it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oueth to be ſeene, like <hi>Druſiss</hi> the <hi>Romane,</hi> who had his houſe full of windows, that all men might behold his conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation: neither is it improbable, but he that had ſeene S. <hi>Paul</hi> when he wrote this verſe, (<hi>Our glory<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:12987:12"/>
                  <hi>is this, the teſtimony of our conſcience</hi>) ſhould haue perceiued the ioy of his heart, euen in his cheerefull countenance. For a ioyfull heart ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth a cheerefull countenance, <hi>Pro.</hi> 15. <hi>ver.</hi> 13.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, we may hence learne what a wofull caſe all Heretickes, Hypocrites, Schiſmaticks, and <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> ignorant men and women are in, whole know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge is peruerted, and who liue in errour. They want the teſtimony of a good conſcience, and therefore a Chriſtian ioy; for there is no true te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony where there is no true knowledge, no true knowledge vnleſſe the ſoule be illuminated by the ſpirit, no true illumination vnleſſe it be guided by the word: theſe therefore hauing ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther knowledge to leade them, nor the ſpirit to enlighten them, nor the word to direct them, are voyde of a true teſtimony, and ſo of a reioycing conſcience. This ought to ſtirre vp all, with all di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence to pray for the ſpirit, to ſeeke after the word of knowledge, to ſay vnto it as <hi>Eliſha</hi> ſaid to <hi>Elias,</hi> I will not forſake thee; to meditate in it day and night. The voyce of wiſedome hath ſounded in our ſtreetes for the ſpace of many yeares toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. And Lord we beſeech thee to defend the <hi>Defender of the faith,</hi> that by his religious care her voyce may long be heard amongſt vs. If the <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> roareth, all the beaſtes of the Forreſt do trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and quake: and ſhall the <hi>Lion of the tribe of Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dah</hi> (deliuer his word)? the <hi>Lion</hi> of the royall Tribe both of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scotland,</hi> both loue and cheriſh the word? Shall wiſedome daily crie
<pb facs="tcp:12987:13"/>
out vnto vs, and not be regarded of vs? When as<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luk.</hi> 1. 41.</note> the mother of this Word went vnto <hi>Iohn Baptiſts mother, Iohn</hi> did skip in his mothers wombe for<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ezech</hi> 37. 7.</note> ioy; when the <hi>Prophet</hi> propheſied to the drie<note place="margin">1. <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4. 16.</note> bones, (<hi>You drie bones heare the word of the Lord</hi>) the drie bones heard it, and ranne together; and at the end of the world the dead ſhall obey it, and riſe out of their graues. O let vs not be worſe then <hi>Babes</hi> in the wombe, then bones vpon the earth, then the dead in the graues. It is the power of God vnto ſaluation; it giueth an inheritance with the Saints; it maketh a man wiſe vnto eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall life; it rectiſieth the conſcience; it is the ground of all true ioy. Let vs take heed we be not <hi>non proficientes,</hi> children in vnderſtanding, euer learning and neuer the wiſer; thoſe that intend truely to reioyce, let them looke into it, for wee can neither haue a good conſcience without the knowledge of the doctrine of faith, nor yet keepe the doctrine of faith without a good <hi>Conſcience.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Particular doctrine vpon the preſent occaſion.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>RIght Honourable,</hi> right Reuerend, and my beloued brethren of this Kingdome of Scotland, attend I pray with patience: So it is (as you haue heard) that there is no true ioy of conſcience, without a ſufficient teſtimony, no ſufficient teſtimony without precedent know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, no knowledge without illumination from the ſpirit and from the word. This then ought
<pb facs="tcp:12987:13"/>
to teach you, that as all times, and in all your acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; ſo moſt eſpecially at this time, and in this great Aſſembly; where there is a generall mee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting for the good of Gods Church; deeply to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſe, and ſeriouſly to looke vnto the teſtimonies of your <hi>Conſcience,</hi> that the end of ſuch a ſolemne action, may be a ſound <hi>reioycing.</hi> Conſult not (I beſeech you) with opinion, imbrace not <hi>Conie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctures,</hi> follow not <hi>affection,</hi> let not will beare the ſwaye; your <hi>loue,</hi> your <hi>deſires,</hi> your <hi>zeale,</hi> your <hi>hatred,</hi> and ſuch like paſſions of the minde ſubdue them vnto <hi>reaſon,</hi> and there is no doubt, but as you haue made a holy beginning; ſo the conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion will be with much <hi>reioycing.</hi> But if <hi>opinion</hi> ſhould proue head-ſtrong, it <hi>contectures</hi> ſhould go for proofe, if fierie zeale, and <hi>blinde affection</hi> ſhould diſpute the cauſe; if you wil retaine <hi>(this)</hi> becauſe you deſire it, or reiect (<hi>that</hi>) becauſe you hate it; if <hi>raſhneſſe</hi> ſhould be thought reſolution, and facti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on wiſedome, (which God be thanked we haue no cauſe to ſuſpect, excepting in ſome few, more weake then wilfull): ſurely (my <hi>Beloued</hi>) the iſſue of ſuch a meeting, could but be a cauſe of farther ſorrow. For according to the errour of the mind, good things will ſeeme to be bad, and bad things to bee good; yea, you will (as <hi>Eſay</hi> complay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth)<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eſay.</hi> 5. 20.</note> ſpeake good of euill, and euill of good, put darkeneſſe for light, and light for darkeneſſe, put bitter for ſweet, and ſweete for ſowre, and ſo come within that cenſure of God, which he pronoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced againſt the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> for doating vpon the
<pb facs="tcp:12987:14"/>
worke of their owne hands: <hi>This people hath mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Exod.</hi> 32. 9.</note> 
                  <hi>all.</hi> To inſtance in foure particulars, vnto which I am confined.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> What is more amiable then <hi>Order?</hi> the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor<note place="margin">
                     <hi>The Earle of Donbars directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</hi>
                  </note> where of is the God of beauty, who hath cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated euery thing in number, weight, and meaſure. <hi>Wiſdome.</hi> 11. <hi>ver.</hi> 17. <hi>Ordo ingreſſus eſt cum Creaturis,</hi> ſaith <hi>Nazianzene,</hi> Order is as olde as the world it ſelfe. We finde it in the <hi>Angels,</hi> we may beholde it in the heauens, one <hi>higher,</hi> another <hi>lower,</hi> one greater, another leſſer: we ſee it in the earth, in reaſonable creatures, in vnreaſonable, in <hi>ſenſitiue,</hi> in ſenſeleſſe, in naturall and in ciuill actions. And therefore hath God much more beautified his <hi>Church;</hi> hath he preſcribed order vnto it? We may in no caſe ſuppoſe, that he hath left it as <hi>monſtrous body,</hi> without ſhape, or as the ancient <hi>Chaos,</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out forme; or as the ſtate of the <hi>Nomades,</hi> without gouernment; no, but he hath made it moſt louely, both in whole, and in parts, as the world well cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated, as a Citie wel ordered, as a Ship wel guided, as a <hi>Cimball</hi> well tuned; not onely <hi>Domus Sapien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiae</hi> (as <hi>Austin</hi> ſaith) the houſe of wiſedome, but <hi>Domus ordinis,</hi> the houſe of order alſo. A Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth is fitly reſembled to the body of a man; and were it not a madde hearing (trow you) if the feete ſhould ſay to the head, wee will weare the hatte? if the knees ſhould ſtriue to car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry the eyes? or if the ſhoulders ſhould claime each of them an eare? But if it were ſo indeede, what a miſ-ſhapen body would this be? Euen ſuch a one
<pb facs="tcp:12987:14"/>
as might well be wiſhed to the diſturbers of a <hi>Kingdome.</hi> Wherefore as in a ciuill gouernment, the hands muſt be content, that the feet do go, the teeth well pleaſed, the tongue tell the whole tale; as the cares muſt not deſire to ſee, nor the eyes to heare; as euery man muſt walke as God hath ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed him; ſo muſt it bee in the <hi>Church of God,</hi> where ſome are eyes, ſome eares, ſome head, ſome<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor</hi> 12. 17.</note> feet; ſome muſt be high, ſome low, ſome rule, ſom obey. This comelineſſe of order is the beauty of<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4. 16.</note> Gods <hi>Church,</hi> for beauty is the daughter of <hi>order,</hi> the more ſeene the more admired; &amp; order is the well diſpoſing of <hi>equall and vnequall things.</hi> Behold then (my beloued) the ſtrength of <hi>paſsion,</hi> if it be not reſtrained. Who would imagine that <hi>Order</hi> could be diſtaſtefull vnto any? ſeeing it commeth from God, is ſeene in euery creature, and is the mother of all beauty in them, attended vpon with infinit bleſſings; yet ſuch is the poyſon which pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> affection, when it is not ruled: as permit it once to giue the teſtimony vnto conſcience, and it wil cauſe men to eſteeme it as a <hi>Iubile</hi> of ioy vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them, to oppoſe and withſtand <hi>order,</hi> yea to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer before it a <hi>popular equality,</hi> which euer amongſt wiſe men hath beene accounted the greateſt <hi>ine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quality.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I ſpeak not this to diſgrace the <hi>Presbytery;</hi> it is a name of <hi>holy record,</hi> and therefore am I bound to mention it with <hi>honor:</hi> yet the power which now it exerciſeth, and place which now it challengeth (<hi>Let me ſpeake truth without offence</hi>) as farre as euer
<pb facs="tcp:12987:15"/>
I could learne is ſomewhat out of <hi>order;</hi> and alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether vnknowen vnto ancient times: if <hi>S. Auſtins</hi> rule be good, the gouernment of the <hi>Church</hi> by <hi>Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops</hi> is Apoſtolicall. <hi>For (ſaith he) whatſoeuer hath beene in the Chriſtian Church in all times, and in all places, vniuerſally receiued without contradiction, is Apostolical.</hi> Such is the gouernment of the Church by Biſhops, in all places, in all times receiued, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer oppoſed, but by ſome few <hi>Heretikes</hi> which were condemned. And leſt I ſhould be thought to contend about words; <hi>S. Paul tels</hi> vs in the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of <hi>Titus,</hi> what theſe <hi>Biſhops</hi> were; <hi>Not modera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors for a yeare,</hi> but particular men hauing the power of <hi>ordination</hi> and <hi>iuriſdiction,</hi> committed<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Tit.</hi> 1. 5.</note> vnto them: <hi>For this cauſe left I thee in Crete, that thou ſhouldeſt continue to redreſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e the things which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine:</hi> there is <hi>iuriſdiction:</hi> and ſhouldeſt ordaine <hi>Elders</hi> in euery City: <hi>here is ordination.</hi> And whereas it is obiected that this power was giuen to one, <hi>propter defectum,</hi> for that there was not as yet a body, or company to be capable of it: I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere that <hi>Paul ſent not Titus into Crete,</hi> as into a new found Iland, but (<hi>left</hi>) him there; and that he <hi>left</hi> him not there to <hi>(plant) a Church,</hi> (for that was done before) but to redreſſe ſome things, which did yet remaine. There was therefore be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore this time a body, or company: And yet it plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the <hi>Apoſtle,</hi> to put this power into one. I doe confeſſe that when <hi>Chryſoſtoms</hi> was baniſhed, one article obiected againſt him was this; that he did not aduiſe in ſome weighty cauſes with his <hi>Preſbyters,</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:12987:15"/>
as hee ſhould haue done. Here was then <hi>Epiſcopus cum Senatu.</hi> A Biſhop with his <hi>Senate:</hi> but <hi>Senatus ſine Epiſcopo,</hi> a Senate without a Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop; a body without a head was neuer heard off, till theſe later dayes. Let the body depend vpon the head, and we ſhall not much diſlike it, for want of <hi>order.</hi> I remember what <hi>S. Paul</hi> doth ſay of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, <hi>that he was troubled with a care for all the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. 28.</note> Had this been ſpoken of <hi>S. Peter;</hi> how would the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi> haue triumphed? So ſay we of Biſhops: that we haue all times and places, Texts of <hi>Scripture,</hi> by a generall practiſe, alwaies vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood for the defence of <hi>Biſhops.</hi> And had the <hi>Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterie</hi> ſuch a cloud of witneſſes, in the affectation of <hi>priority,</hi> how highly would it aduance the <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigne</hi> of honor? But in <hi>compariſon of a Biſhop,</hi> I muſt haue leaue to ſay vnto it, as <hi>Christ ſaith</hi> vnto one, that did chooſe the chiefeſt place: <hi>Priend giue this</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>I like</hi> 1 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>man the roome, he is more honourable then thou.</hi> The conſent of all Churches in all times, together with the warrantiſe of Gods word, giues precedency in power, and in place to the <hi>Biſhop.</hi> And here is a ground for a good teſtimony of the <hi>conſcience;</hi> wherefore the <hi>conſequent</hi> of an action tending to ſuch an end, will doubtleſſe be a ſound and a <hi>holy icy.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> what was euer eſteemed more ſweet <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> then peace? The <hi>Orator</hi> tels vs, that the very name thereof is ſweet, it ſelfe much more: like the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious <hi>ointment</hi> vpon the head of <hi>Aaron,</hi> that ranne downe vpon his beard, and from his beard to the<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſalme</hi> 133.</note>
                  <pb facs="tcp:12987:16"/>
skirts of his <hi>clothing. Pacem te poſcimus omnes.</hi> They are frantique men, that fall out with peace. The old <hi>Gentiles</hi> loued her ſo well, as that they made her a <hi>Goddeſſe.</hi> And <hi>Tiberius</hi> dedicated a <hi>Temple</hi> vnto her in <hi>Mount Palatine</hi> (as we may reade in <hi>Suetonius.</hi>) When <hi>Salomons</hi> Temple was a buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, there was not a ſtroke heard, nor the noyſe of a <hi>hammer.</hi> That <hi>King</hi> of peace, when he buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded a Temple for the <hi>God of peace,</hi> would haue it e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen in the doing, to acknowledge both the end and <hi>Author. Ioſephus</hi> giues a reaſon why the <hi>Iewes</hi> ſo louingly did offer Sacrifice one for another; becauſe (<hi>ſaith he</hi>) they held themſelues to be fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes, hauing one Temple to one God, common to all, being the common God of all. When <hi>Chriſt</hi> came into the world, his <hi>Angels</hi> did ſing a <hi>ſong of peace:</hi> whiles he continued in the world, he preached <hi>peace</hi> to men: when he went out of the world, he left his peace as a <hi>legacy</hi> vnto his <hi>Church:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Acts</hi> 2.</note> In the <hi>prime</hi> age whereof, the <hi>Diſciples</hi> agreement and peace was ſuch, as if there had beene but one <hi>Soule</hi> amongſt them. In the time of <hi>Tertullian</hi> (as himſelfe reporteth) this was the <hi>Romans</hi> obſerua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which they made of the <hi>Christians, Vide vt ſe inuicem diligunt Chriſtiani.</hi> See how theſe <hi>Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> doe loue one another; they knew themſelues likewiſe to be fellow members, hauing (<hi>Christ Ieſus</hi>) one head, to one body, common to all, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the common head of all. Our <hi>Religion</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth <hi>à Religando,</hi> whereby (ſaith <hi>Nazianzene</hi>) thoſe which belong vnto God, are made one with
<pb facs="tcp:12987:16"/>
him: Thoſe which be ſonnes of the <hi>Spirit,</hi> become hot in loue: Thoſe doe beare one anothers bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens, which belong vnto him, that bare all our burthens. Let vs come lower vnto our ſelues, Since the preaching of the <hi>Goſpell</hi> in this <hi>Iland</hi> wherein wee liue, wee haue beene <hi>kiſſed</hi> with the <hi>kiſſes</hi> of <hi>peace.</hi> Our <hi>gouernment</hi> hath beene peace,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eſay</hi> 60. 18.</note> 
                  <hi>Saluation</hi> our walles, and <hi>praiſe</hi> our <hi>gates.</hi> And as <hi>Tertullus</hi> doth to <hi>Foelix</hi> in the ſtory of the <hi>Acts;</hi> ſo<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Acts</hi> 24.</note> muſt we wholly acknowledge in all places, with all thanks to God, that we haue obtayned, and doe now enioy many excellent bleſſings by the means of peace. Were it not then beyond all meaſure <hi>monſtrous,</hi> that any ſhould be ſo toſſed with the tempeſt of deſires, as not to loue <hi>peace,</hi> ſo ſweet in experience, and imbraced of all? The <hi>Apoſtle</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandeth vs to keepe the <hi>vnity of the Spirit, in the</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4. 3.</note> 
                  <hi>bond of peace,</hi> and as farre as it is poſſible to haue<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 12. 18.</note> 
                  <hi>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ace</hi> with all men. The <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> willeth vs to ſeeke <hi>peace</hi> and to enſue it. We haue one <hi>God,</hi> one <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpell,</hi> one <hi>King,</hi> one <hi>Continent.</hi> The diuiſion of <hi>tongues,</hi> was the <hi>confuſion</hi> of <hi>Babel.</hi> The <hi>diuiſion</hi> of the heart, is the <hi>death</hi> of the <hi>Soule.</hi> The diuiſion of minds, is the ouerthrow of <hi>Kingdomes.</hi> The diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of <hi>Gods</hi> people, is the deſtruction of his <hi>Church.</hi> If we bite one another, we ſhall be conſumed one of another. And yet behold, <hi>peace</hi> may take vp<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gal.</hi> 5. 15.</note> that <hi>complaint</hi> that <hi>God</hi> once made againſt his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eſay</hi> 1. 2.</note> 
                  <hi>Iſrael. I haue nouriſhed</hi> and brought vp <hi>children,</hi> but they haue rebelled againſt me. <hi>Miſchieuous ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> contents</hi> deuoted to <hi>ſelfe loue,</hi> &amp; fetching the ioy of
<pb facs="tcp:12987:17"/>
their <hi>Conſcience</hi> from a deceiptfull <hi>teſtimony;</hi> ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe themſelues to be <hi>cold</hi> in <hi>Religion,</hi> vnleſſe they be <hi>hot</hi> in <hi>faction.</hi> And ſo doe they lay about them,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 24. 18.</note> as if the <hi>Altar</hi> ſtood ſtill vpon <hi>Araunahs</hi> threſhing<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 140. 2.</note> floore. Their ſtudy is to ſtirre vp <hi>ſtrife</hi> all the day<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Tſal.</hi> 7. 14.</note> long. <hi>Deſtruction</hi> and vnhappnies is in their waies, and the way of <hi>peace</hi> they haue not knowen. They trauaile with miſchiefe, and in their beds appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for reſt, they plot how to be <hi>turbulent,</hi> and to<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 7. 15.</note> bring forth their vngodlineſſe. And ſo far are they from deſiring of <hi>peace</hi> betweene <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>Kirke,</hi> from maintaining of <hi>peace</hi> between man and man, as they want many times that loue or inclination which <hi>one Beast</hi> doth beare vnto another. If one <hi>Sheepe</hi> be faint, the reſt will ſtand betweene it and the Sunne till it bee comforted; if one <hi>Hogge</hi> bee hunted, the whole <hi>heard</hi> will muſter together to reuenge it. It is reported of <hi>Bees,</hi> that <hi>Aegrotante vna, lamentantur omnes.</hi> If one be ſicke all are ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry: Yea ſome <hi>Beasts</hi> are more kinde to mankinde, then ſome men to themſelues. <hi>In humane ſtorie</hi> we reade of <hi>gratefull Lyons, of kinde Eagles, of trusty Dogges. Qui mori pro Dominis, &amp; commori cum Dominis parati</hi> (as <hi>Ambroſe</hi> writeth.) <hi>In holy Bible</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. <hi>King.</hi> 17.</note> we finde that <hi>Elias</hi> was ſedde by <hi>Rauens;</hi> and that<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Dan</hi> 6. 22.</note> 
                  <hi>Daniel</hi> was not hurt amongſt hungry <hi>Lyons. O detestandam humane malitiae crudelitatem?</hi> ſaith Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prian, <hi>Aues paſcunt; ferae parcunt; homines ſaeuiunt.</hi> O hatefull cruelty, the <hi>Birds feede,</hi> the beaſts fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour; but ſuch is the rage of a miſ-informed <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience,</hi> as that one man will ſhew himſelfe a wolfe
<pb facs="tcp:12987:17"/>
vnto another. Theſe wherſoeuer they be (<hi>I charge not this place</hi>) are the troublers of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> are thornes in our <hi>eyes,</hi> and pricks in our <hi>ſides,</hi> diſmembring the body, and renting the coate of <hi>Chriſt, that ſame Tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nica</hi> which was <hi>vnica,</hi> that coate without Seame. Out of a falſe Teſtimony <hi>perhaps</hi> they may pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe <hi>peace</hi> vnto themſelues, yet (as <hi>Hierome ſaith</hi>) <hi>Tranquillit as iſta, tempeſt as eſt,</hi> their calme of <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience,</hi> will one day proue a <hi>ſtorme.</hi> The <hi>God of</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eſay</hi> 57. 21.</note> 
                  <hi>peace</hi> giue vnto them a true <hi>teſtimony</hi> of their <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience,</hi> that they, and we, and all, may ioyntly ſing a <hi>ſweet ſong of peace</hi> together, and make vp a full <hi>conſort and harmonie of heauenly ioy.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thirdly, obedience</hi> to our King is a duty moſt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary.<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> 
                  <hi>Nature</hi> commendeth it, <hi>Scripture</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandeth it, <hi>Preſent</hi> danger pleadeth for it. <hi>Rex vnus est apibus, Dux vnus eſt Gregibus</hi> (ſaies <hi>Cypri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an.</hi>) Among the Bees there is one Maſter, amongſt the flocks of Sheepe one <hi>Belweather.</hi> The <hi>Cranes</hi> haue their captaine, <hi>quem ordine literato ſequantur,</hi> whom the reſt doe follow (as <hi>Hierome obſerueth.</hi>) Paſſe we from <hi>nature</hi> of leſſer force, and come we to <hi>Scripture</hi> of greater power. <hi>Let</hi> euery <hi>Scule</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 13. 1.</note> be ſubiect to the authority of <hi>higher powers</hi> (ſaith <hi>S. Paul</hi>) A peremptory propoſition, inforced by manifold reaſons. Firſt, all powers are of <hi>God;</hi> the <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> 
                  <hi>higher from the higheſt.</hi> Secondly, they bring with them the good of <hi>order;</hi> for the <hi>powers are ordeined.</hi> Thirdly, it is <hi>ſinne</hi> to diſobey them, for <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> hee that reſiſteth authority, reſiſteth Gods <hi>ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Verſes.</hi>
                  </note> Fourthly, Iudgements <hi>temporall</hi> and <hi>eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall</hi>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:12987:18"/>
doe accompany this ſinne: They that reſiſt,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> ſhall receiue to themſelues <hi>damnation.</hi> Fiſtly, <hi>Gouernment</hi> is the meanes of our <hi>weale he is the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter of God,</hi> for thy wealth. Wherefore we muſt <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> needs obey; and <hi>obey;</hi> not only for feare of <hi>ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance,</hi> but alſo becauſe of <hi>conſcience. Our obedience</hi> is acceptable to <hi>God, who enioyneth it,</hi> &amp; profitable to our ſelues, who enioy the good of <hi>gouernment</hi> by it: And therefore <hi>neceſsitate finis, &amp; praecepti,</hi> both in reſpect of end, and of command, it is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary we ſhould obey. <hi>Our Sauiour Chriſt,</hi> by his precept and by his <hi>practiſe</hi> ſheweth that we owe <hi>ſubiection;</hi> howſoeuer ſome would exempt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues. <hi>Chriſtus aliter iuſsit aliter geſsit,</hi> (as <hi>S. Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nard</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luke</hi> 20. 25.</note> ſpeaketh;) He taught otherwiſe: <hi>Giue vnto</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>John</hi> 19. 11.</note> 
                  <hi>Caeſar that which is Caeſars:</hi> He wrought otherwiſe: for he ſubmitted himſelfe vnto the <hi>Roman Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate.</hi> His <hi>Apoſtles</hi> did treade in their Maſters ſteps:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Acts</hi> 25.</note> 
                  <hi>Paul</hi> appealed vnto <hi>Caeſar,</hi> and appeared before <hi>Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſar</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Jude</hi> 8.</note> as his lawfull Gouernour: <hi>S. Iude</hi> deteſted them as falſe <hi>Prophets,</hi> who deſpiſed gouernment, and<note place="margin">1. <hi>Peter</hi> 2. 13.</note> ſpake euill of thoſe that were in <hi>authority. S. Peter</hi> exhorteth all, to ſubmit themſelues to all manner <hi>ordinance</hi> of man, for the <hi>Lords ſake.</hi> In the dayes of the <hi>Apoſtles, Kings,</hi> and <hi>Gouernours,</hi> were wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhippers of <hi>Diuels,</hi> and moſt <hi>cruell</hi> perſecutors of the <hi>Christian faith.</hi> O how are we bound then to honour a <hi>religious King,</hi> which is a <hi>defendor of the faith,</hi> and a nurſing Father vnto the <hi>Church of God?</hi> How needfull a thing is it, that <hi>his will</hi> ſhould be done, who commandeth for the <hi>truth, &amp; non tam</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:12987:18"/>
                  <hi>de nobis quam à nobis,</hi> and done, <hi>I ſay,</hi> not ſo much (on vs) as (<hi>of vs?</hi>) If we muſt yeeld to <hi>the ſroward,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 <hi>Peter</hi> 2. 13.</note> with what gladueſſe of heart ſhould we expreſſe our <hi>obedience</hi> to the good and courteous? now as <hi>Scripture</hi> preſcribeth this; ſo doth <hi>danger plead</hi> for it. <hi>Rex est in medio Inimicorum.</hi> Though thouſands of faithfull <hi>Subiects</hi> ſtand round about him, yet many a falſe hearted <hi>Papist</hi> preſſeth neare vnto him. The <hi>Proteſtants</hi> are not more ready to defend him; then the <hi>Popiſh ſort,</hi> are to write againſt him. Thone ſide labour not more to preſerue, then the other to <hi>diſturbe,</hi> and <hi>ouerthrow</hi> his Kingdomes. Their bloudy <hi>practiſes,</hi> both at home and abroad; hath ſtamped them for <hi>King-Killers,</hi> and made them <hi>odious</hi> to the <hi>world. Now my beloued,</hi> the <hi>Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eccleſiaſt.</hi> 4. 12.</note> tels vs, <hi>that a three-fold corde is not eaſily broken.</hi> Here is <hi>Nature, Scripture, Danger,</hi> to binde vs in <hi>obedience.</hi> But alas theſe are like <hi>Sampſons cords,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iudges</hi> 15. 14.</note> but as <hi>flaxe</hi> that is burnt with the fire, vnto ſome fiery <hi>and ſurious ſpirits.</hi> Who when they are in ſtrongeſt <hi>oppoſition to their King,</hi> deem themſelues to be in <hi>deepeſt denotion to their God:</hi> then moſt cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragious, when they are moſt factious: and ſtouteſt <hi>Champions</hi> for <hi>Chriſt,</hi> when they moſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tend with <hi>his annointed: ſcorning men</hi> of an obedient <hi>would,</hi> as if they were but dull and <hi>drowſie fellowes.</hi> What? <hi>(my Brethren)</hi> ſhall nature call vpon vs; and <hi>Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture</hi> command vs; and ſhall we ſtoppe our eares? ſhall the King be next the <hi>fire: (it is your owne phraſe,</hi> I haue learned it from your ſelues) and will you thruſt him in? will you giue him cauſe to ſay
<pb facs="tcp:12987:19"/>
vnto you as <hi>Christ</hi> to his <hi>Apoſtles. Will you alſo for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake me?</hi> Hath he not a rabble of <hi>rebellious Popists</hi> to withſtand him? but will his <hi>Protestants</hi> alſo reſiſt him? Will you gainſay the godlieſt, the wiſeſt, the <hi>louingest King,</hi> that euer you enioyed? no; you will not, for howſoeuer an <hi>erronious conſcience,</hi> may make no <hi>conſcience of diſloyaltie,</hi> yet your <hi>holy Conſent</hi> in this <hi>publique buſineſſe,</hi> declares your <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences</hi> to be better informed.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fourthly,</hi> There is almoſt no greater ſlauerie then to yeeld <hi>Subiection</hi> to the <hi>Pope,</hi> who is a <hi>Clog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maker</hi> for <hi>Conſcience:</hi> and whoſe rules, are <hi>Snares</hi> to the <hi>Soules of men;</hi> who albeit he calles himſelfe the <hi>Seruant of the Seruants of God;</hi> yet, as <hi>Austin</hi> ſaith of <hi>Antichrist, Let vs obſerue, ad quid v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>it, non quid ſonat,</hi> what his deedes are, not what are his<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iob</hi> 41.</note> words; and we ſhall finde him, as <hi>Iob</hi> ſpeaketh of the <hi>Leuiathan,</hi> the <hi>King</hi> of the children of <hi>pride;</hi> and therefore the Maſter ſeruant of the <hi>ſeruants of the Diuell.</hi> The power which he now challengeth is moſt <hi>extravagant;</hi> they call him <hi>Dominum mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tium, &amp; Dominum vallium,</hi> the Lord of the <hi>Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines,</hi> and the <hi>Lord</hi> of the valleyes: and S. <hi>Peters Keyes</hi> are ſo improued, as <hi>piſcatores hominum</hi> are become <hi>piſcatores imperiorum;</hi> Fiſhers of men, fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhers of <hi>Monarchies.</hi> That <hi>ruffling Prieſt of Rome</hi> dares now be bolde, <hi>cum Leonibus, tanquam cum Agnis Ludere,</hi> to depriue Kings of their States, to diſcharge <hi>ſubiects</hi> from their <hi>obedience,</hi> to incroch vpon <hi>Quarters,</hi> which neyther belong to <hi>Church,</hi> nor <hi>Church-yard:</hi> ſwimming in his <hi>Sea,</hi> with the
<pb facs="tcp:12987:19"/>
bladders of <hi>Ambition;</hi> drowning the <hi>Church</hi> in her owne bloud, and turning <hi>Hieruſalem,</hi> the <hi>Citie of peace,</hi> into <hi>Acheldama</hi> the field of bloud. Will you endure to heare what this man can do? He is able iudicially to pardon <hi>ſinnes,</hi> and to retaine them at his pleaſure, to binde and vnbind, to play faſt and looſe like a <hi>Iugler;</hi> to diſpence with an Oath, if neede require, and for (a good childe) at a pinch with Gods commandements. What can he not doe, if you will beleeue him? Pleaſeth it you to know what his <hi>Holiſhip</hi> hath done? (<hi>ex vngue Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onem,</hi> from a few thing eſteeme of the reſt) Hee made the Emperor <hi>Fredericke</hi> to hold his <hi>ſtirrup: Lodowicke</hi> to take his <hi>Crowne</hi> and <hi>poſſeſsions</hi> at his hands: <hi>Otho</hi> the firſt, <hi>Henry</hi> the ſift, <hi>Sigiſmonde,</hi> and <hi>Charles</hi> the firſt to kiſſe his feete. <hi>Inuenit aliquid infra genua quo libertatem detruderet,</hi> as <hi>Seneca</hi> ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth of <hi>Caligula.</hi> He excommunicated <hi>Otho</hi> the fourth, <hi>Henry</hi> the fourth, <hi>Philip,</hi> and the <hi>Fredericks,</hi> firſt and ſecond. His <hi>Bulles</hi> haue come bellowing, and his <hi>Breues</hi> bluſtering, againſt the <hi>perſon</hi> of a late <hi>Noble Queene,</hi> and againſt the <hi>purpoſes</hi> of our <hi>Royall King.</hi> VVill you heare what he is? He is the <hi>Sonne</hi> vpon the <hi>Earth, the Prince</hi> of the <hi>world,</hi> (and ſo is the Diuell too) an <hi>Vniuerſall Biſhop,</hi> not a meere man, but a <hi>God,</hi> hauing <hi>plenitudinem potestatis,</hi> for theſe are <hi>titles</hi> giuen him by his <hi>Canonists.</hi> Time will not ſuffer me, to deſcribe him as I would. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough hath becne ſpoken<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> to ſhew you that <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lish Miniſters are no Popiſh Prieſts,</hi> who hold him no better then <hi>Meridianus Daemon</hi> (as <hi>Bernard</hi> cals
<pb facs="tcp:12987:20"/>
                  <hi>Antichrist</hi>) then that <hi>noone Diuell,</hi> who from the hill of <hi>pride,</hi> hath deceiued the world, blinded the people, corrupted the faith, peruerted the <hi>Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures,</hi> confounded <hi>Diuine</hi> and <hi>humane Lawes.</hi> And yet beholde once againe (my <hi>beloued</hi>) whither a blinde zeale, of a bad <hi>conſcience</hi> doth carry many men? Are not diuers as faſt tyed to this man of <hi>Sinne</hi> as the eare of a <hi>Slaue</hi> was wont to be nayled to the threſhold of his <hi>Master?</hi> If he ſaith come, they come; if goe, they go; if poyſon, if murther, if practiſe <hi>Treaſon,</hi> if ſtabbe <hi>Kings</hi> and <hi>Princes,</hi> if runne to the <hi>Diuell,</hi> they are ready for to doe it; yeelding their abſolute <hi>obedience,</hi> without making queſtion. O the admirable force of <hi>Conſcience: ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hemens eſt in vtranque partem,</hi> which way ſoeuer it taketh, it is puiſſant and powerfull. If it be not well grounded, it preferreth <hi>parity</hi> before <hi>Order, diſcord</hi> before <hi>peace, diſloyalty</hi> before <hi>obedience, ſlaue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie</hi> before freedome: and as it dealeth in theſe, ſo according to the teſtimony, true, or falſe, doth it make or marre all our actions, and fill vs with a true or counterfeit <hi>ioy.</hi> Let it be our care therfore I beſeech you, now and euer to looke vnto our te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimonies. And the God of wiſdome guid vs with his ſpirit, and giue vs knowledge in his word, that hauing our vnderſtandings illuminated, and our <hi>Conſciences</hi> ſanctified, wee may doe thoſe things which are pleaſing in his ſight, that our <hi>hearts</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bounding with true ioy in this life, we may enter into our Maſters ioy in the life to come. Heare vs
<pb facs="tcp:12987:20"/>
                  <hi>deere Father, God of all ioy and comfort,</hi> euen for <hi>Christes ſake,</hi> to whom with thee and the <hi>holy Spirit,</hi> be all <hi>praiſe, power,</hi> and <hi>domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion</hi> now and for euer. AMEN.</p>
               <trailer>FJNJS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
